Finding aid for the Experiments in Art and Technology records, 1966-1993 (bulk 1966-1973)
Experiments in Art and Technology records
- Project files, 1966-1992, 1966-1973; Series I.; 112.5 lin. ft. 121 boxes, 7 flat file folders, 1 roll
  - TELEX: Q & A, 1971 (Box 66)
    - Original telexes (Box 66, Folder 1-13)
      of questions and answers from all 4 stations filed in rough chron. order with a small quantity of correspondence interspersed (N.B., many telexes are long, rolled or folded and very cumbersome to handle).
  - TELEX: Q & A, 1971 (Box 67)
    - Q&A compilation (Box 67, Folder 1-18)
      contains mostly photocopied telexes of questions and answers cut and stapled onto sheets, filed according to city where question originated, and 2 sets of photocopied sheets.
  - TELEX: Q&A, 1971 (Box 68)
    - Q&A compilation (Box 68, Folder 1-10)
      photocopies of sheets (see above) and of original uncut telexes, ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 68, Folder 11-28)
      includes correspondence with Nakaya, Hulten and others pertaining to organizational matters, ca. 50 items; notes; initial question drafts; lists of unanswered questions; correspondence soliciting answers from various knowledgeable individuals and responses, ca. 45 items; Q&A tallies; drafts and final version of compilation ("ms." which E.A.T. hoped to publish); and 26 photos, 4 contact sheets (2 by Shunk-Kender) and negatives of telex machines and Utopia exh.; ca. .5 lin. ft.
  - TELEX: Q&A, 1971 (Box 69-76)
    New York Times, August 1981 (Project's questions were aimed at ten years from 1971. E.A.T. collected the "New York Times" for one month for later study on how 1981 differed or resembled the predictions, guesses and feelings people had about it in 1971.).
  - New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973 (Box 77)
    - Proposal (Box 77, Folder 1)
      drafts and final version.
    - Correspondence (Box 77, Folder 2-19)
      includes carbon copies and photocopies of form letters sent by Klüver, Martin, Barbara Birkenmeier (Project Director) and Constantine Vasiliadis (Chairman, Friends Committee) to potential sponsors and donors, committee members and artists primarily regarding organizational matters, fund-raising and portfolio sales with some responses, Jun 1971-Sep 1974. Also contains a letter from Hans Haacke making many inquiries as to E.A.T.'s programs and how the sale of the collection will benefit E.A.T. (Mar 3, 1972, folder 2) with a response; extensive quantity of mailing lists; and much Moderna Museet correspondence which includes a cc. of a letter from Paik to Hulten about transferring and shipping a videotape for his work in the collection with a short explanation of its contents, announcement for Rauschenberg's "Pelican," 3 issues of "Meddelande till Moderna Museets vanner" (nos. 1, 11, 12), 2 postcards of Rauschenberg's "Monogram," telexes and telegrams about last minute details, including Klüver's description of how "Mude Muse" should be installed (Oct 12, 1973) and shipping of works; ca. .75 lin. ft.
    - Fund-raising (Box 77, Folder 20-21)
      includes potential sponsors and priorities lists; notes; form letter drafts; and proposed budget.
  - New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973 (Box 78)
    - Artwork for collection (Box 78, Folder 1-5)
      notes on artwork contacts with pertinent information on each piece; notes on promised artworks with 3 color transparencies, neg., 6 photos, and 3 negatives of Walter De Maria's "Hard Core," note and letter from Paik, "Ad Reinhardt: Black Paintings 1951-1967" catalog, and Richard Serra drawing on Castelli stationary as seen in catalog; many photocopied loan forms; invoices from galleries and artists; and photocopied bills of sale and deeds of gift; ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Collection catalog (Box 78, Folder 6-8)
      includes some correspondence; lists and descriptions of works; 15 negs.; and catalog copies.
    - Print portfolio (Box 78, Folder 9-18)
      includes many carbon copies of letters to artists; note from Jasper Johns; mss.; proofs; illus.; production costs and sales; security agreements; and correspondence and mailing lists for portfolio donations (1976, 1981); ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - P.R (Box 78, Folder 19-22)
      press releases and kits; mailing lists; and miscellaneous.
    - Opening and reception, Oct 27, 1972 (Box 78, Folder 23-25)
      invitations, notes, and mailing lists.
  - New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973 (Box 79)
    - Portfolio Print Collection
      collection of 30 lithographs, silkscreens, photoprints and a record, by 30 artists, measuring 30.3 x 22.7 cm. (9 x 7 in.), 21 of which are signed and numbered A.C. 12/30 (edition size of 300), 1973. This portfolio is not housed in a mahogany box.
  - New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973 (Box 80)
    - Stockholm trip, Oct 25, 1973 (Box 80, Folder 1-10)
      includes carbon copies of opening invitation letters; note and postcard responses from Robert Morris, Hans Namuth, Diane Waldman, Blanchette Rockefeller and Douglas Davis (ca. 40 items); flight and hotel accounting and people lists; activities; mailing lists; notes; and miscellaneous; ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Financial (Box 80, Folder 11-15)
      much correspondence regarding portfolio sales and payment of debts, especially to artists for their works, such as Walter De Maria (letter from Oct 17, 1973), Oldenburg, Dine, Stankiewicz and Noland. Also includes budgets, expenses and receipts.
    - Notes (Box 80, Folder 16-21)
      substantial regarding opening and other matters, ca. .25 lin. ft.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 80, Folder 22-29)
      includes drafts and reports; invitations; leaflet (1979); and reference articles.
  - New York Collection for Stockholm, 1971-1973 (Box 81-86)
    Index cards with addresses for dinner with Princess Christina of Sweden at Rauschenberg's house.
  - Membership lists, undated (Box 87-94)
    Index cards of artists and engineer members, California address list and others.
  - Television Projects, 1970-1975 (Box 95)
    - Antenna Proposal, 1970 (Box 95, Folder 1)
      notes and correspondence.
    - RCA Television Laboratory, 1970 (Box 95, Folder 2)
      proposal with notes and draft versions, and some correspondence.
    - Twenty-six Television Programs, 1970 (Box 95, Folder 3)
      proposal titled "E.A.T. Cookbook."
    - USA Presents (Box 95, Folder 4-5)
      Bicentennial Satellite, 1971: includes correspondence; proposal; TV distribution study; clippings; and notes.
    - Two Pre-Investment Studies for UNDP (United Nations Development Program), 1971 (Box 95, Folder 6-12)
      includes proposal and correspondence with Dr. Vikram Sarabhai, U.N. and World Bank, and correspondence regarding Super 8.
    - UN Satellite Demonstration, 1975 (Box 95, Folder 13-14)
      notes and correspondence
  - Artists and Television Project and Artcash Benefit, 1971 (Box 96)
    - Artists and Television Project (Box 96, Folder 1-16)
      includes letters to artists inviting them to submit proposals (Feb 1971) with a negative response from Jasper Johns; artists' program proposals from Oldenburg, Trisha Brown, Ed Ruscha, Robert Breer, Pauline Oliveros, Keith Sonnier, Dean Stockwell, Richard Serra, Michael Snow, Robert Creeley, George Kuchar, Robert Irwin, Larry Poons, Jean Dupuy, Paik, and others; program schedules; budgets; grant requests; and final list of participants. Also contains agreement; budget; expenses; and press releases from Automation House and Sterling Manhattan Cable regarding equipment rental and gallery (for exhibition and sale of artists work to fund the project; see also Artcash Benefit); ca. .33 lin. ft.
    - Artcash Benefit (Box 96, Folder 17-43)
      includes correspondence with persons interested in receiving bills, galleries with price lists and some reproductions of works (2 big folders), and regarding loan confirmations; lists of contributing galleries and artists in the exhibition; consignment receipts; catalog manuscript; master price list for Artcash bills; artists' money arrangement; photocopied artists' statements relating to currency/money (see Boxes 98-102 for actual bills); mailing lists and invitations; accounting, receipts, bills and closing agreement; and miscellaneous; ca. .66 lin. ft.
  - Artcash Benefit, 1971 (Box 97)
    Andy Warhol $1 Artcash ink pad stamp: used on envelope of mailing for Artcash Benefit in 1971.
    Pitney Bowes printing plates: used on mailings that went out: "Participation not Patronage," "Enjoy the Hardware," "We Love Pitney Bowes," "Process not Product," "Trust the Artist," "Artist Engineer Collaborations in the Industrial Environment" and "We Involve Professionals from Anywhere."
  - Artcash Benefit, 1971 (Box 98-102)
    5 bundles of ca. 500 bills each of Artcash by Andy Warhol, Rauschenberg, Jeff Davis, Marisol and Whitman.
  - Projects in Central America, ca., 1966-ca. 1972, undated (Box 103)
    - Research material concerning television, 1969-1972 (Box 103, Folder 1-31)
      Mostly in the form of reports and articles concerning television in education for developing countries and E.A.T.'s projects in television, Alpha files A-P include 17 color transparencies from Bell Labs of technology and 16 photographs of nature for a proposed publications brochure; many articles on Computer Assisted Instruction; proposal for El Salvador; comments of various organizations to the Federal Communications Commission's notices of inquiry; and recording of indigenous cultures ( 1972, see miscellaneous).
  - Projects in Central America, ca. 1966-ca. 1972, undated (Box 104)
    - Alpha files S-W (Box 104, Folder 1-15)
      Includes papers by Wilbur Schramm and on Sesame Street. Similar material to Box 103.
  - Projects in Central America, ca. 1971-ca. 1974, undated (Box 105)
    - El Salvador (Box 105, Folder 1-7)
      includes organizational correspondence; telexes between Klüver in El Salvador and E.A.T. staff; proposal and drafts; meeting notes; bidding instructions for an instructional television studio and broadcasting equipment; and equipment catalogs; ca. .33 lin. ft.
    - Guatemala (Box 105, Folder 8-20)
      telexes to Klüver in Guatemala from E.A.T. staff about multi-dimensional scaling questionnaire and using film for educational purposes; background and general information; notes; report drafts and final report; and a substantial quantity of multi-dimensional scaling questionnaires; ca. .66 lin. ft.
  - Miscellaneous oversize, 1970-1971 (Box 106)
    Includes 3 publications for Projects in Central America; "Software" exhibition cat., 1970; five photographs by Evelyn Hofer; cash disbursement ledger, Jan 1970-Jan 1971; payroll ledger, Jan-Sep, 1970; and general ledger, 1971.
  - Printed Ephemera, 1960s-1990s, 1971-1972 (Box 107)
    - Printed ephemera (Box 107, Folder 1-14)
      In the form of announcements, invitations, catalogs, bulletins, press releases, clippings, sent to E.A.T. from various sources.
  - Various publications on education and television, 1966-1975 (Box 108)
    - Reports, 1966-1975 (Box 108, Folder 1-14)
      Includes "Access" nos. 11 and 14 (1973, 1975); UNESCO "Music and Technology," 1971; NEA/NCA " 1970 Annual Report" and five year fiscal report 1966-1970; and UNESCO and Ford Foundation reports.
  - Video Research A-M, mid 1970s (Box 109)
    - Publications, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 1-23)
      Mostly publications, catalogs and articles collected in support of video projects, filed alphabetically by subject. This includes information on public media, equipment, exhibitions, laboratories; clippings on museum and artist activity; and journals and magazines, such as Criss Cross Double Cross. (See oversize Box 106.)
  - Video Research A-M, mid 1970s (Box 110)
    - Publications, printed matter (Box 110, Folder 1-25)
      Similar to Box 109, includes files on National Endowment for the Humanities, NY State Council on Arts, video performances, proposal for video festival, video art, video expo, 1975-1976, videography and video & music.
  - Island Eye Island Ear, includes:, 1974-1979 (Box 111)
    - Correspondence (Box 111, Folder 1-3)
      organizational in nature, documenting difficulties finding a site, ca. 35 items.
    - Notes and research (Box 111, Folder 4-8)
      mostly on site locations and antenna (see also Boxes 112-113).
    - Financial (Box 111, Folder 14-16)
      NEA grant proposal and budget.
    - Press (Box 111, Folder 17-25)
      clippings from local newspapers publicizing event and expressing concern over concert's potential harm to the environment; press release and Klüver letter to Adirondack newspaper about concert cancellation; and some biographical material relating to Tudor, Nakaya and Jackie Monnier and interview drafts with each.
  - Island Eye Island Ear, 1974-1979 (Box 112)
    - Proposals, reports on islands (Box 112, Folder 1-21)
      Extensive quantity of proposals, reports and descriptions of Bluff Island (some with photos), and of a few other islands.
  - Island Eye Island Ear, 1974-1979 (Box 113)
    - Maps, sketches and some photographs of locations (Box 112, Folder 1-23)
      See also flat file folder 6** for more maps.
  - Various Projects, includes:, 1975-1992 (Box 114)
    - Calder Bicentennial Project, 1975 (Box 114, Folder 1)
      proposal.
    - "Paris-NY-Paris" opening at Centre Georges Pompidou, 1977 (Box 114, Folder 2-16)
      E.A.T. organized charter flight. Includes telex correspondence concerning general organization and giving detailed installation instructions for Marcel Duchamp's "Etant Donné" and Rauschenberg's "Oracle"; travel payment letters from Louise Bourgeois, William Wilson, Francois De Menil, Larry Rivers, Richard Stankiewicz, and many others; letters of interest and cancellation; RSVP and charter registration forms; Pompidou invitations, programs, and trip schedules; guest and accommodations lists; notes; travel invoices; financial; and information on satellite program; ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Robert Whitman Archive, 1977 (Box 114, Folder 17)
      includes photocopied clippings; essay on Whitman by Klüver and Martin; archival processing plan; and a permanent installation plan; ca. 20 items.
    - Artist Data Base (for contemporary artists), 1977 (Box 114, Folder 20)
      includes notes and proposal, ca. 25 items.
    - Berlin Trip (to see Robert Wilson's opera "Death, Destruction and Detroit"), 1978 (Box 114, Folder 23)
      mailing lists; announcement drafts; schedules; notes; and travel guides; ca. 25 items.
    - List of Fahlström's works (with prices), Jul 1979 (Box 114, Folder 24)
    - Katzive Project (video project with Lucas Samaras), 1987 (Box 114, Folder 30)
      grant proposal.
    - Rolando Peña, 1992 (Box 114, Folder 34)
      mostly photocopied articles/reviews and 36 slides, ca. 65 items.
  - Transportation Study and Multi-Dimensional Scaling, 1977 (Box 115)
    - Transportation Study, 1977 (Box 115, Folder 1-12)
      Applies "impact scaling" methods to transportation policy planning in the NY state area. Mostly photocopied research articles, and also proposal drafts, meeting notes, copies of letters sent and notes, ca. .33 lin. ft.
    - Multi-Dimensional Scaling, 1977 (Box 115, Folder 13-16)
      meeting notes, proposal drafts and printout of computer source code.
  - Multi-Dimensional Scaling, 1968-1972 (Box 116)
    - Multi-Dimensional Scaling Workshop, research papers, 1968-1973 (Box 116, Folder 1-7)
      Includes documents and papers given at Bell-Penn Multi-Dimensional Scaling Workshop (Jun 7, 1972-Jun 10, 1972), and numerous research articles on the topic, 1968-1973 (bulk early 1970s). (N.B. This box was treated for extensive mold damage, and items are exceptionally fragile and mold-stained.)
  - Multi-Dimensional Scaling, undated (Box 117)
    IBM punch cards for multi-dimensional scaling program from Doug Carroll, Bell Labs.
  - Artists for New York Benefit, 1979 (Box 118)
    - Correspondence, documents, printed matter (Box 118, Folder 1-28)
      Consists of correspondence, report, artists' committee name lists and letters to, information letter, 3 folders of notes mostly pertaining to "to-dos" and invitations, mailing lists, budgets, publicity, press releases, artists' and others requests for tickets, texts for invitations, invitations and mailers, tickets, programs.
  - Trisha Brown Co., 1980 (Box 119)
    - Material for "Opal Loop/Cloud Installation,", 1979-1980 (Box 119, Folder 1-20)
      Collaboration with Nakaya, "Glacial Decoy" (with Rauschenberg), and general information on TBC. Includes fund-raising letters from Julie Martin and Rauschenberg to prospective patrons; thank-you letters from Brown to sponsors; "Glacial Decoy" performance instructions and invitations; Nancy Graves Poster material (donated by Graves and used for 1980 NY season and for promoting Europe performances); "Opal Loop/Cloud Installation" notes, sketches, diagrams, patent application pertaining to Nakaya's fog [see also flat file folder 7** for plans of fog system and architectural plans and sections of Brooklyn academy of Music, Opera House], press release, tickets and invitations. Also includes clippings; articles; announcements; programs; a profile on Brown; and Merce Cunningham press clippings and press release.
  - Klüver Talks, Lectures and Articles, 1968-1992 (Box 120)
    - Manuscripts (mostly photocopied), notes and correspondence, 1968-1991 (Box 120, Folder 1-60)
      Pertaining to "Technology and the Individual," Spring 1968 (proposed book); Minneapolis School of Art, May 9 1968 (commencement address); "The Ghetto and the Technical Community," Summer 1968 (article); "The Artist and Industry," Dec 16 1968 (lecture at MOMA); "Artists, Engineers and Technology," 1969 (paper written with Rauschenberg for "International Conference on Technological Change and Human Development," Israel); "Rainforest," Jan 30 1970 (article on history of E.A.T.); "Establishing an Interactive Relationship Between the Artist and Technology," Jun 1969 (for 1970 edition of "Enciclopedia della scienza e della tecnica mondadori"); "Conditions for Artists Participation in Shaping the Environment," Feb 22 1976 (presented at the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science); detailed corrections of National Gallery of Art's Rauschenberg Retrospective catalog, 1977 (14 p.); "Artist Expertise for Communication Plannings," Sep 13 1977 (paper given at the International Institute of Communication); "9 Evenings: Theatre and Engineering," 1980 (article in "Für Augen und Ohren"); corrections to Calvin Tomkins "Off the Wall," 1980 (3 p.); "9 Evenings," 1980-1991 (talk); "Pavilion," Aug 12 1990 (talk at Queens Museum); and "9 Evenings," Sep 3 1991 (talk at Neue Pinakothek, Munich); among others, arranged chronologically.
  - Klüver Talks, Lectures and Articles, 1968-1992 (Box 121)
    - Manuscripts and printed articles (Box 121, Folder 1-12)
      Contains "Art Engineering and Collaboration," Apr 12 1992 (talk at DIA conference) and some mss and articles by others (John Pearce, Max Mathews, Francis Mason and James Tenney).
  - Oversize project files material
    - Printed ephemera (Oversize 1**)
      Poster: Artists' benefit sale for Encounter Inc, April 30 - May 1 1972.
    - Pepsi Pavilion, logo design artwork, undated (Oversize 2**)
      14 sheets with colored marker and pencil sketches. [Relates to material in Box 44.]
    - Pepsi Pavilion - hardware drawings (Oversize 3**)
    - John Pearce's files - Pepsi Pavilion (Mirror Dome) (Oversize 4**)
      Photomechanical drawings, some annotated. [See also Box 48, f.10-14.]
    - Projects outside art - Greenhouse plans (Oversize 5**)
      [Relates to material in Box 60, f.3-17.]
    - Island Eye, Island Ear maps (Oversize 6**)
      [Relates to Boxes 111, 112, 113.
    - Trisha Brown Co. - Opera House - Fog system plans (Oversize 7**)
      Relates to Box 119.
    - Expo 70 architectural drawings (Oversize 2**)
      Festival plaza, float assembly drawings, Pepsi pavilion. [Relates to Box 45, f. 28-31; Box 48, f. 16-24.]
- Correspondence and administration, 1966-1980; Series II.; 21 lin. ft. 16 boxes
  Considerable correspondence with artists, engineers, sponsors, and staff members about various topics, such as membership, finances, fund-raising and projects, arranged in rough chronological order. There are also general files mostly consisting of correspondence and publications, arranged in alpha order. The administration of E.A.T.'s policies and procedures are documented with by-laws and board of directors meeting minutes, and office management and fund-raising files. This series also contains a large quantity of Klüver and J. Martin notes.
  - Correspondence, 1966-1974 (Box 122)
    - Klüver, 1966-1974 (Box 122, Folder 1-26)
      general correspondence with arts organizations, journals, corporations, government officials, universities, and artists, discussing such matters as sponsorship, information requests, invitations for Klüver to speak, collaboration ideas and projects. Highlights are letter and note from Cage who needs technical assistance with 2 compositions (1967) and requests E.A.T. to give money that is owed to him to Sari Dienes (1968); 7 letters with Eugenio Carmi about establishing an Italian E.A.T. local group (1967-1968, see also Box 30, Local Groups); note from John Kenneth Galbraith (Aug 17 1967); correspondence with Senator Jacob Javits and wife Marion (ca. 15 items, 1967-1968 and Jan 1972); letter from Betty Asher at LACMA requesting information for their art and technology project (Jul 10 1967); 4 items with Lil Picard about reviews (1967); note from Harold Prince (1967); letters to John G. Powers, Aspen Inst. of Humanistic Studies, about board formation and other organizational matters with a response addressed to Rauschenberg (13 items, 1967-1968); 8 p. typescript to Jan Butterfield, Fine Arts Associates, concerning E.A.T. LA (Feb 1968); postcard from Anaïs Nin mentioning a Stanford seminar on the relationship between integrated circuits and her work, and asking Klüver to send written materials on his ideas so she can introduce him "in the Diary" (Dec 1969); two letters from Kaprow about receiving "tax exempt financial acknowledgment" as part of the Pavilion settlement (May 1 1971); and letter from Charlotte Moorman (undated, ca. Oct-Dec 1971). From 1970 onward, the correspondence contains more photocopies and carbon copies from Klüver regarding the organization and fund-raising of specific projects, such as Telex: Q&A, Artists and Television, and New York Collection for Stockholm. Many of these letters document severe budgetary problems. 1967-1968 filed in rough alpha order by institution, and 1969-1974 filed in rough chron. order; ca. .5 lin. ft.
    - Klüver correspondence with Fujiko Nakaya, 1969-1974 (Box 122, Folder 27)
      primarily long detailed letters from Nakaya discussing E.A.T. Japan organizational matters with many comments about proper etiquette and red-tape encountered when interacting with Japanese officials and cultural leaders; collaboration with and support from Takashi Asada (environmental developer); project ideas; updates on Japanese television technology, especially that which Sony has developed; and the potential to deal art and exhibit Pop art in Japan. Also contains 4 p. letter from Nakaya describing the negative situation of the Expo Festival Plaza (Aug 21 1970), ca. 90 items.
    - Klüver correspondence log, 1973-1974 (Box 122, Folder 28)
      kept by Barbara Birkenmeier Jan 1973-Aug 1974.
    - Francis Mason (President of E.A.T.), 1968 (Box 122, Folder 29-39)